Finding Aid for Dept. of Germanic Languages and Literatures (University of Michigan) records, 1929-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dept. of Germanic Languages and Literatures (University of Michigan) records 1929-2009
University of Michigan. Dept. of Germanic Languages and Literatures.
1.6 linear feet
2009143 Bimu 2
Germanic Languages and Literature became an independent department at the University of Michigan in 1807, prior to that German language was taught under Modern Languages. Course offerings expanded to include German, Swedish, Norwegian, Gothic, Netherlands, and Yiddish. Departmental records pertaining to curriculums staffing, events, faculty, and the operation of the department. Minutes date from 1929 to 1941, and 1985-2000. Faculty files include William H. Bennett, Francis Brown, Martin Dyck, John W. Eaton, Emery George, Otto Graf, Leta Lewis, Henry Nordmeyer, Clarence K. Pott, Walter Reichart, Alice Tramm, Frederick B. Wahr, and Norman Willey.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Accessions received from the Department of Germanic Languages and Literatures (Donor No. 9288) beginning in 2005. Dutch Language program material was received in 2009 ( 7443 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The Department of Germanic Languages and Literatures records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Department of Germanic Languages and Literatures record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Box 2
In 1847, the University of Michigan incorporated modern languages into its program of study with the introduction of French language and literature courses taught by Louis Fasquelle, LL.D., who had been appointed to the university the previous year. Instruction in German began in 1849, and replaced courses in Spanish and Italian that had begun in 1848. When German was introduced in 1849, the course of instruction in modern language was comprised only of two terms of French (one taken in the sophomore year and the other in the junior) and two terms of German (both to be completed during the junior year). In 1854, Fasquelle became the first professor of Modern Languages and Literature, and at the same time at which the German requirement for classical studies students was increased to three terms. In 1858, undergraduate lectures in German literature were added to the list of approved coursework for the master's degree. With the exception of one course in German literature, the German course of study was confined to written and oral grammar and translation exercises. It was not until Edward P. Evans joined the department (in 1862 on the death of Fasquelle), that the department included course offerings in German literature and Germanic philology.
Throughout the latter part of the 19th century the German program at the university experienced continued growth in faculty, students, and courses. The first professorship in German was made in 1887 when Calvin Thomas (1887-1895) became Professor of Germanic Languages and Literatures. It was at this point that the modern languages course of study was officially divided into two independent departments; the Department of Germanic Languages and Literatures and the Department of Romance Languages and Literatures. In this year the department offered its first seminar in German, and Swedish and Norwegian were introduced as new alternate year course offerings. The Department's curricular offerings broadened in the period between 1889 and World War I to include new courses and programs of study in Middle High and Old High German, 18th and 19th century German literature, literature of the Reformation, lyric poetry, linguistic science, the history of German literature, Old Icelandic, Old Saxon, Gothic, Old Norse Faust, folklore (German and Old Saxon), German for engineering students (including descriptive prose and scientific German), and modern German sounds and syntax.
On the eve of World War I, the Department of Germanic Languages and Literatures instructed a quarter of all the students enrolled in the literary and engineering colleges, an amount larger than other of the other modern languages. Upon the United States' entry into the War, however, the Department and the university as a whole saw its enrollment rates for men plummet. Like its counterparts at other universities, the Department of Germanic Languages and Literatures fell prey to the nativist and anti-German sentiments of the times. In October 1917, the Board of Regents of the University dismissed Dr. Carl E. Eggert from the German Department. Eggert was accused by a prominent Michigan alumnus, Geology Professor William H. Hobbs, and German Professor John W. Scholl of sedition and promulgating pro-German propaganda in the classroom. Soon after, in March 1918, five additional German professors (Richard O. Ficken, Hermann J. Weigand, John Dieterle, and Warren W. Florer) were discharged for ideological reasons. Although the Regents presented scant evidence of the men's alleged pro-German sympathies, neither Eggert, nor his colleagues were to be rehired by the university. The dismissals of the six faculty members effectively cut the Department's faculty in half, with only four faculty remaining, one of whom was shifted to teaching French. Enrollment in the Department dropped to fewer than 100 students, from a peak of 1,300.
The interwar period witnessed the slow rebuilding of the Department's faculty, and a gradual increase in the number of classes offered, and the number of students enrolled. These gains continued through the fall of 1932, at which point the Depression's detrimental effects had become clear. By 1933, the Department's enrollment rates were at their lowest ever and it was not until 1935 that the numbers began to increase steadily once again.
During World War II, many of the Department's older faculty feared that the Department of Germanic Languages and Literature would disappear, as had almost happened in the wake of World War I. This proved not to be the case, however, and the war years were in fact a period of growth for the Department. While there was a decrease in the number of male students entering the Department as they and some faculty, such as Professor Otto Graf, enlisted in the armed forces, the Department experienced increased prominence during the war years for its involvement in the Army Specialized Training Program. The Department instructed thousands of soldiers and sailors in its intensive language and area studies courses.
The Department of Germanic Languages and Literatures continued to grow in the post-war period, in part as a result of its work during the war years and also due to the tremendous expansion of college enrollments at the university. During the 1950s and 1960s, the Department expanded its collaborative initiatives by participating in Michigan's Great Books Program for undergraduates, including comparative literature graduate students in the Department, supervising the work of high school teachers of modern languages, establishing the Deutsches Haus on campus (known as the Max Kade German House in honor of its benefactor Max Kade), and partnering with other universities to establish a Junior Year Abroad in Freiburg, Germany.
In the 1950s and 1960s the Department also dramatically expanded its curricular offerings. It added courses at both the undergraduate and graduate levels in an array of fields including, medieval literature, 16th and 17th century works, 19th and 20th century prose fiction, literary criticism, and modern and contemporary literature. The Department also expanded its scope of Germanic languages, reintroducing programs in Scandinavian (Norwegian, Swedish, and Old Norse language and literature) and Netherlandic. In 1967, the Department initiated a program in German language and readings as part of the foreign language offerings in the newly formed Residential College.
The Department continued to strengthen its curriculum in the 1980s with the additional courses in Scandinavian. In 1984, the Department revived its outreach efforts with middle and high school German instructors and their students by starting "German Day." "German Day" consisted of a series of fun competitions for middle and high school students (including contests in speaking, reading, poetry recitation, skits, art projects, and musical performance) designed to celebrate German language study, while at the same time introducing students and their teachers to the Department of Germanic Languages at the University. In 1986, in an effort to improve outreach to alumni, the Department initiated a newsletter U of M Germanic News.
In the mid-1990s the Department once again undertook a review of its undergraduate programs. By 1996 most first year courses were taught by tenured or tenure-track faculty, and the Department had once again expanded its course offering to include undergraduate classes on mathematical and scientific German, German crime stories, post-War politics and society, the Magic Flute, and literary interpretation. The Department's commitment to undergraduate education was recognized by the students and the University when the Department won the LSA Student Government Departmental Excellence Award in 2002 and 2004.
Departmental Chairs
1887-1895 Calvin Thomas
1895-1899 George A. Hench
1899-1900 George Hempl
1900-1929 Max Winkler
1929-1934 John W. Eaton
1935-1960 Henry W. Nordmeyer
1960-1971 Clarence K. Pott
1971-1976 V.C. Hubbs
1976-1979 Claiborne W. Thompson
1979-1985 Roy C. Cowen, Jr.
1985-1991 Robert L. Keyes
1991-1992 Frederick R. Amrine
1992-1995 Robert L. Keyes
1995-2004 Frederick R. Amrine
2004-2007 Geoffrey H. Eley
2007- Helmut Puff
Records from the University of Michigan Department of Germanic Languages and Literatures were received in three accessions from the department in 2005, 2006, and 2008. The material is described as one collection and is primarily comprised of records related to departmental administrative functions, events and publications, curriculum, and faculty. Files document departmental meetings, graduate and undergraduate curriculum, rotational reviews, staffing plans, personnel information, and faculty.
The records measure 1.6 linear feet, and date from 1929 to 2009, with the majority of materials from the period between 1945 and 1980. The records are primarily comprised of correspondence, minutes, personnel materials, and administrative files and are arranged into five series: Administrative, Curriculum, Events, Publications, and Faculty.
Subjects:
George, Emery Edward, 1933-; Germanic languages--Study and teaching.; Graff, Otto G.; Language and education.; Language and languages--Study and teaching.; Reichart, Walter Albert, 1903-1999.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Germanic Languages and Literatures.; Wahr, Frederick B. (Frederick Burkhart), b.1889.
- Administrative
  The Administrative series, 1929-2000 (0.25 linear ft.), contains minutes of Department and Executive Committee meetings from 1929-1941 and 1985-2000, reports from the Committee on Foreign Language Instruction, information regarding the awarding of honorary degrees, rotational (internal) review materials, diversity issues, and long-range staffing plans.
  - Belgian American Education Foundation Fellowship 1989 (Box 1)
  - Diversity Issues 1988-1992 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Foreign Language Instruction 1950-1954 (Box 1)
  - Honorary Degrees 1965-1987 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of Meetings
    - Departmental Meetings 1929-1941, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Department Executive Committee 1985-2000, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Netherlands Visiting Professor 1987, 2001 (Box 1)
  - Promotions 1989-1995 (Box 1)
  - Rotational Review 1984 (Box 1)
  - Staffing Plan 1984-1993, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Curriculum
  The Curriculum series, 1966-2002 (0.3 linear feet), consists of records on Dutch Area Studies, the graduate, undergraduate and Residential College programs. Material on Dutch Area Studies includes correspondence with Willard Wichers and the Consulate General of the Netherlands pertaining largely to visiting lecturers. The graduate materials folder includes information on departmental requirements for the graduate program in the early 1990s. The undergraduate file consists of materials related to the administration of the undergraduate curriculum from 1991 to 2002, including committee reports and policies. The Residential College folder includes materials relating to the Department's involvement in the College's founding through its external review in 1998.
  - Dutch Area Studies 1968-1996, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Graduate 1986-2004 (Box 1)
  - Undergraduate 1991-2002 (Box 1)
  - Residential College 1967-1998 (Box 1)
- Events
  The Events series, 1990-2003 (0.2 linear feet), contains information on conferences, film series, and lecture announcements sponsored by or affiliated with the department.
  - Conferences
    - Critical Theory and Alternate Modernities 1996 (Box 1)
    - Fulbright Education Experts Seminar 2000 (Box 1)
  - Film Series 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Lecture Announcements 1990-2003 (Box 1)
- Publications (Box 1)
  The Publications series, 1975-2009 contains newsletters that chronicle faculty hires and retirements, research projects, faculty publications, conference updates, notifications of honors, grants, fellowships, and awards, as well as updates on graduate and undergraduate students and alumni. Also included is a single copy of the journal Michigan Germanic Studies from 1975
  - Michigan Germanic Studies, 1975 (Box 1)
  - U of M Germanic News, 1986-1995 (Box 1)
  - Departmental of Germanic Languages and Literatures Newsletter, 2005-2009 (Box 1)
- Faculty
  The Faculty series, 1933-2007 (1.5 linear ft.), includes university personnel records, faculty correspondence, curricula vitae, course materials, instructor evaluations, promotion and tenure materials, and letters of recommendations. Although materials in this series cover the period 1933-2007, the bulk of the materials are from the mid 1940s through the mid 1970s. The faculty series also includes records relating to departmental Chairmen, including John W. Eaton, H.W. Nordmeyer, Clarence K. Pott, and V.C. Hubbs. (In accordance with university policy, personnel related records, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files, are restricted for thirty years from date of creation).
  - Personnel Files 1946-1967, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Faculty Files
    - Bennett, William H. 1959-1981 (Box 2)
    - Brown, Francis Andrew 1946-1962 (Box 2)
    - Cowen, Roy C. Jr. 1986 (Box 2)
    - Dyck, Martin 1952-1969 (Box 2)
    - Eaton, John W. 1933-1948 (Box 2)
    - Gaiss, A.J. 1945-1960 (Box 2)
    - George, Emery E 1955-1988, 4 folders (Box 2)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2018 ]
    - Graf, Otto 1939-1993
      - Awards (Box 2)
      - Biographical (Box 2)
      - Correspondence (Box 2)
      - Course Material (Box 2)
    - Green-Gantzberg, Vivian Yvonne 1974-1984, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Lewis, Leta J. 1941-1962 (Box 2)
    - Hubbs, V.C. 1961-1963 (Box 2)
    - Markey, Thomas 1973-1987, 2 folders (Box 2)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2017 ]
    - Nordmeyer, Henry W. 1938-2000 (Box 2)
    - Paslick, Robert 1963 (Box 2)
    - Philippson, Ernst A. 1935-1943 (Box 2)
    - Pott, Clarence K. 1943-1993 (Box 2)
    - Reichart, Walter A. 1935-1999 (Box 2)
    - Scholl, John 1939-1952 (Box 2)
    - Scholler, Harald 1969-2002 (Box 2)
    - Schottler, Peter,1996 (Box 2)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2026 ]
    - Trumm, Alice 1958-1988, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Wahr, Fred B. 1936-1984 (Box 2)
    - Wheelis, Samuel M. 1967-1975 (Box 2)
    - Willey, Norman L. 1936-1959 (Box 2)